So, in today's video, I'm going to show
you why doing good SEO doesn't always
drive more AI visibility using a
real-life example. My name is Nathan
Gotch and I'm the co-founder of
Rankability and author of the upcoming
book AI SEO for Dummies. Let's dive
right in. What we're going to do today
is we're going to focus on how to drive
more visibility for healthy beef jerky
for this random e-commerce brand that I
picked. I don't have any association
with them, so they're just getting a
free full strategy on the house, okay?
So, what we're going to do very simply,
we're not going to go super crazy here
because the strategy for them is
actually quite simple. What we need to
do is we need to build more topic
support and then we need to expand that
topic support onto other owned assets
and then we need to focus on earned
media and even some distribution. I'm
going to show you this is so simple as
far as the strategy that you should be
able to develop a strategy in one day
and begin the process of execution,
okay? Just to give you some context,
when we when we go after a particular
category, we're usually focused on one
category for anywhere between 90 days to
180 days, okay? So, just one category
and that's to make sure we absolutely
cover it to the fullest extent. And
truthfully, most businesses never do
this. This is a massive mistake, okay?
You have to go a mile deep on these
topics, all right? So, first thing you
want to do is just establish the
benchmark. So, yet last week I ran this
and then I ran it again today and you
can see there hasn't been much change
since, but that's actually not the thing
I care most about in here. What really
pops out to me as I mentioned at the
beginning of the intro of this video is
this brand is doing really well in
traditional search, okay? So, when we
look at traditional search, you can see
they're ranking number three. They have
great search coverage across the four
major search engines and they've even
got a secondary URL that's popping up in
here as well. So, they've got two
different URLs that are ranking in the
let's say the top 25, which is great,
okay? So, they're doing a really good
job in traditional search. But the
problem is when we look at AI citations
or AI answers, why is their brand not
being mentioned in these answers? Okay,
when we look in ChatGPT, they are not
present, right? And they're not present
even in the product carousel. When we
look across any of these, they are not
being mentioned by the AI. And this is
going to hurt sales. They're missing out
on sales right now by not being
recommended. So, this is really
important that you first of all, you
need to be tracking this and you need to
no matter what tool you use, you should
be tracking this because you need to see
are we actually getting recommended by
the AI in our most important categories,
okay? And this is a very broad category
here, very competitive, but they need to
have some brand visibility here. They
need to have the AI recommending them.
So, the question is, how do we do it?
Okay? So, my favorite thing to do right
now is simply just go to the AI
citations. This is most of the work that
we do these days. We go into the
citations, we extract the citations, and
then we see if the brand is mentioned.
Very simply, you just click this button
and you can just see are they being
mentioned? And this is telling us
everything that we need to know as to
why they don't have visibility in AI
answers. They're only mentioned four
times across 82 citations. 82 citations,
they're mentioned four times. Three of
those are self-serving, okay? So, the
reality of this is that they basically
have one, if you want to call it, which
is probably from a product carousel in
Google AI mode. So, they don't really
have any mentions at all. So, when you
think about that, imagine you're the AI
and you're trying to give a good list of
the best healthy beef jerky, but you've
got this brand that no one ever talks
about, no one ever recommends across any
of your sources, right? That's how the
AI is working. It's working through
these different sources and then looking
for consensus. And whatever based on
that consensus is, it's going to show
those brands more and that's why you're
going to see Archer Jerky showing up
basically everywhere because they are
cited, they are mentioned, they are
recommended across almost every single
citation, okay? This is It is actually
this simple. So, when you're thinking
about, okay, what's the work that we
have to do? You export this, and I'll
show you in a second what this looks
like, but you export this and you start
to just work through these lists for the
ones that you can actually get, okay?
Now, if you want to do this in a smart
way, you come in here and you run
multiple, so you go in here and you run
multiple reports, and then you simply
just go like this and you export to a
spreadsheet, and what this will do is
just export all of the traditional
search results and all of the AI
citations. I like to export them all
out, and then I can get a really good
idea of what I'm working with, all
right? So, basically what I'm doing is
I'm looking at, okay, what are the
opportunities? First of all, you can
learn so much from this, by the way.
This is like people greatly
underestimate this the opportunities
that exist just by studying what
actually shows up in AI citations and
traditional search. So, for me, I can
look at this and I can see tons of
opportunity that can basically help me
formulate my whole strategy in a very
short amount of time. So, looking at
this, all right, couple things that pop
out to me right away. Number one, let's
walk through the earned media
opportunities, all right? So, this
column right here, I've already marked a
lot of these, and you can see these are
basically all different blogs, news
websites. This is a press release here.
So, this means we should also run a
press release. If you open this up, you
can see that this is clearly a press
release about whatever their new brand
is, business wire. We can run these
ourselves, too. And it the fact that
it's getting picked up as a citation
tells us what we need to know. In AI
mode, it's getting picked up, okay? So,
once again, this gives us an opportunity
to expand our reach, expand our
influence. This is really important that
we see this. So, right there, that's
easy. The rest of these are all
basically all just blogs, okay? These
are all just different blogs, and you
can see here, we could just reach out
directly to these blogs, whatever they
are, and just see if we can get brand
mentions here. Clearly, this is a really
good one because they're they're These
are affiliate links. So, this ends up
being like 20-ish
earned media opportunities. And this is
just from a very simple export. There's
only about four different topics.
Imagine you multiplied this by 10 or 20
topics, you'd have a list of a couple
hundred opportunities easily that you
could go and promote your brand on. So,
this is what you need to be doing
because if you're not visible in the AI
answers, it's very likely because you're
not visible in the core sources of
retrieval. It's that simple. So, what
I'm doing is I'm looking at the earned
media opportunities. I highlighted these
because we see Facebook, we see
Instagram, and we see YouTube, okay?
Those are three different owned media
opportunities, which tells us if we see
that Facebook's popping up and I see
that Instagram is also popping up, and
then I see a YouTube, we can attack this
on two different fronts. We can attack
it from the perspective of building out
our own content to attack these exact
queries, and then also reaching out to
influencers and trying to get them to
recommend us on these platforms as well
because clearly they're getting picked
up by these various AI platforms, right?
And we can see Google organic,
Perplexity AI mode, we can see Brave,
Perplexity, Deep Seek. This is for
Reddit specifically. And Reddit, once
again, is an earned media opportunity,
but you can get you can infiltrate
Reddit pretty easily these days, okay?
It's not super hard. But the point is
this is what you should be doing. And
another thing that popped out to me was
I saw Target, right? We see Target in
here. I see Walmart in here
specifically, and then I saw Amazon is
in here as well. So, the reason I'm
showing you this is because when we go
over and we map this out, okay? This is
what we're looking at here.
So, [snorts]
just from that simple export, I can
already learn so much. And also with
doing a little bit of keyword research,
okay? So, I'll show you real quickly
here. Little bit of keyword research,
just ran a little report, and then just
built this very simple list, okay? And
in this simple list, I can start to see
a lot of these different topics where we
can build more support. So, this green
box here, this is the stuff that they're
already doing really well. So, if you go
and look at their site, you can see
they're already hitting on a lot of
these kind of secondary categories,
these supporting categories. This is
really smart, super good. I can tell
either they're they have an in-house SEO
that's pretty solid, or they're working
with a good agency because there's no
way they would have formulated this well
without having a good strategy in place
cuz this is like good, like really good.
So, I'm impressed. That's great. But,
they are there are gaps still, okay? We
even when we look at that, there's still
gaps. And the gaps are just getting more
granular. Now, if I had access to their
Google Search Console, I would just pipe
that right in here, and I'd be
extracting even more very granular
queries and different types of intent
from Google Search Console cuz it's much
more rich with information. I don't have
access to their data, so I can't do
that, but I can still get some really
good ideas looking at trending topics,
looking at YouTube, just pulling from
Google, obviously. And what I was able
to find is look at all these gaps that
they have here. It's stuff related to
paleo, weight loss, bodybuilding, and
then even specific types of vitamins,
zinc, magnesium, vitamin D. These are
all separate dedicated intents that
you'd want to build out assets for to
attack these, right? And then, the next
one here, which matters a lot, is cut
competitor comparisons, okay? So, their
top competitors are being used in
retrieval quite a bit. So, what I would
do is I want to attack their these
queries around their competitors. So,
the best one you can do is alternatives.
You start with alternatives. You begin
as that your seed. So, I'll show you an
example of this. I already built one out
just for fun. You can see that I just
did Archer Jerky alternatives, okay? And
you can see how quick I was able to
build this out. Absolutely solid asset
here, ready to go. This is the template
that works. So, you can just take this
if you want, but this is the type of
asset I would build. I would repeat this
across every single competitor. I do
Archer Jerky, I would do People's
Choice, I would do so on and so forth,
every single one. Then, the next thing I
would do is I would expand that
competitor comparison. So, this one we
would call just basically, we'll call it
we'll say plus alternatives, okay?
That's the first part. Then, what I do
is I would expand to something like
this. So, it'd be competitor like this
versus competitor like that. And then, I
would do versus us,
okay? These are the best. These are
absolutely the best because it kills two
birds with one stone. You can rank for
the competitor queries. So, it might be
Archer Jerky versus Perky Jerky, right?
So, you'll end up ranking for that
query, but then you slap yourself in
there, and then you easily able to
promote your stuff in that page, right?
So, what we do is we will build these
out on the website. We will attack every
single angle of this. And then, we'll
take those same exact topics, and we'll
hit them again, Facebook, Instagram,
YouTube. So, basically, what you've done
is you've built out topic authority on
your website, which is your home base.
You should absolutely do that. Once
you've tapped it out, then expand. I
recommend expanding into YouTube because
YouTube has so much influence, and start
to attack those same topics there. So,
what ends up happening is just by doing
that alone, we can see what will happen
very clearly is we will have already
done well with our website, but we'll go
over here, and we'll see the YouTube
specifically, right here, we've got
about This is uh four different videos
that are popping up. And look at the
coverage that they have across different
platforms. Imagine you attack this but
with great depth across all the
different topics. It's going to be
pretty interesting how quickly you can
attack YouTube. And it's actually funny,
there are actually some YouTube Shorts
popping up in here, but this is for
Google organic and AI mode. Maybe Gary
is right in some instances on this one
because that that actually does show
that attacking YouTube Shorts might be a
good secondary category on YouTube as
well. But I think long-form is going to
probably influence more. So, you want to
go ahead and attack that on YouTube and
then expand into Facebook and Instagram.
Once again, don't overthink this. You
just take the same topics, but you just
make sure that the content format
matches whatever distribution channel
you're using, okay? Then what we're
going to do here is very simply, like I
said, focus on the offside
opportunities. And then going back to
distribution, you can see Amazon,
Target, and Walmart. I looked on Amazon
and their brand is not on there. They're
not on Target and they are not on
Walmart. So, we're talking about three
massive e-commerce distribution engines.
These are huge. And so, if I was this
brand, like, why would we not be trying
to get distribution on these three
platforms, these three huge
opportunities for sales? I'd be spending
a lot of time on that. And they're
actually being used in retrieval as
well. So, definitely an area that you
would want to attack, okay? Now, aside
from That's basically it. That's all you
need to do is just build that build the
topic authority, go super hard on that,
okay? And then all that is really left
at this point is you just have to really
attack this category with everything you
have, okay? It's easy to develop the
strategy. It's hard to execute, okay?
But the reality is you can do so much
just on your site and just on your owned
assets alone. And it's just there's so
much opportunity. So, I would highly
recommend attacking this much more. And
once again, stay focused on this
category. And what you do is over time,
as you build that out, you want to see
that you're starting to get more
mentions in the AI answers. Okay, that's
what we're looking for. So, by doing all
of this work, you're tracking every
single time that you're developing. Now,
this is one thing I want to make very
clear here. There's a lot of people that
are just wasting money on tracking.
Okay, I want to be very clear. But, I'm
just telling you most people waste are
wasting their money on tracking, all
right? This is what I do when I track,
all right? So, let's say I'm going after
best healthy beef jerky. And what you
can do is obviously set up tracking and
track this every day, but there's no
point of tracking performance every day
if you aren't working on that category.
So, what I do is I do a benchmark
report, which means this is just a
snapshot. This is not I'm not tracking
this. And so, when we start to do work,
what I do is I come down here and I will
start to annotate, right? So, okay, so
we published this, we published that.
And I can see that timeline of work
that's being done on this. Then, I run a
scan, okay? So, that's what I'm doing.
I'm doing work, I'm annotating, and then
I'm running scans. And that way I can
see, okay, we did this on this date, and
I can see the performance of how that
changed over time, right? You're not
going to be able to say that one asset's
what did it, but you can clearly see
over time when you see that this is
starting to influence a lot more, you're
just going to start seeing that growth.
Okay, you're going to start seeing more
visibility. Okay, and so then the last
piece of this is when you have attacked
all the obvious topics, the next thing
you want to do is build more topic
support around this with informational
content. Now, a lot of people get this
messed up, including this brand. When I
actually look at this, you can see like
this one here, why high protein snacks
are a great idea. What you want to do is
you want to build stuff that's
research-driven, data-driven, stuff that
can help you attract backlinks
naturally, can get shared on social
media. We're talking real content
marketing, not just kind of generic
stuff that AI could spin up in 2
seconds, right? So, what do you do?
Here's what you can do. You can use AI
to your advantage. So, very simply,
we'll go here and you can see I already
set this up so you can see just using
ChatGPT, you can use Claude, doesn't
make a difference, okay? All the models
are so smart now. You can use pretty
much any of them. So, you can see here
this is a very simple prompt. And so you
can see you can copy this prompt if you
want, but basically I want the AI to
give me ideas that are specific to this
category. This is the most critical
part. If you come into ChatGPT and say,
"Give me link bait ideas." It's not that
useful. Even if you say, "Oh, we're a
beef jerky company, give us link bait
ideas." It's not that useful. You want
to get real focused on just that one
category cuz you get way better ideas.
So, this is a great example. You can see
there's tons of beautiful examples in
here. And they're grounded, too, cuz you
know that they're grounded because it
actually did research, okay? So, this is
all good. So, basically what I did is I
went through this and then I looked at
one that I thought was interesting and
had it expand more. So, all I said was
just conduct deep research on this
topic. It cooked for 12 minutes, okay?
12 minutes on this topic, just going
absolutely crazy. And that's what you
want to see. It's going super deep on
this. And the end result of this is a
really well-researched,
let's call it paper, right? Like we got
tons and tons of grounding, tons of data
that we can use here to our advantage.
And like specific use cases and
timelines, all right? So, could you take
this and just slap it on your website?
Probably, but I wouldn't recommend that.
I would just use the research and
convert it into a very structured asset.
But more importantly, what I would do
first is I think about design. How do I
design this? Once again, AI these days
is makes life a lot easier. So, you can
see here I just said, "Create a prompt
for my design agent for the visual
assets to support this data-driven
study."
That's simple, okay? I'm just going to
go right into Claude design. So, we can
see here I pasted that exact prompt. I
didn't do anything wild. I just the
exact prompt in here. It asked some
clarifying questions. I literally just
skipped them cuz I just wanted to get
through this quicker. And you can see
here this is the full prompt and you'll
see I skipped all the questions, the
clarifying questions, and I just let it
cook. So, it built out tons of different
assets, okay? And we can see it's got
the jerky Jen's kind of design system in
here. And once again, this is not going
to be like perfect out of the gate, but
it gives you a really nice base to work
from. And we can see it's already really
good and it just needs some slight
refinement. Sometimes you'll see some
hallucination and so on and so forth,
but the point is you can dig into this
and you can start to just focus on
editing, okay? These days the key to
using AI is you don't ever need to start
with a blank canvas basically ever. The
magic is in the edit. This is even
before AI. When it came to writing, the
magic of writing was always in the edit.
It was never in just the writing, right?
The edits are what what make it happen.
And this is true with design, it's true
with AI content, it's true with AI
coding. It's really the editing where
all the magic happens, but the key is
you're building hyper-focused content.
And the only way to do it at this level
is to be category focused. If you try to
be super broad, it's just too hard. So,
this is what I would recommend doing.
And this is just one asset, right? If we
go into chat GPT, we can see there were
25 different angles that you could
attack just in this one category. I can
guarantee you your competitors are not
doing this, okay? So, that's the
strategy I would use to dominate the
category of healthy beef jerky. Hope
that helps and I'll see you in the next
video. Thanks.